[Music]
so I've been fascinated ever since we
interviewed Richard tarnis and I saw on
Richard Thomas's book a quote from you
and then also realized after we
interviewed Iain McGilchrist that you
were friends with him also and I'm
really interested in what it is that you
that you find compelling about about
their thought they're talking about the
things that I find most interesting and
most important which are a long way from
what most people interested in because
I've always been interested in stuff to
do with psychology of almost every time
and I'm also interested in spiritual
stuff in a very weakened form which is
what I what I call why we're here
is there a purpose of life and of course
the current scientific paradigms there's
no purpose at all consciousness is an
epiphenomenon caused by chemical so
chemical reaction which i think is
complete nonsense it reminds me of what
George Orwell once said which was only
an intellectual could believe that
Richard Thomas in particular I read
passion of the Western mind in
University and I think it had more
impact on me than anything else I've
ever read you were interested in
Richards work before Ian's or what was
the sequence
I read the passion of the rest of world
before I met Richard Thomas and the
moment we met
and that was at Esalen we just clicked
and I love being around people who are
much much cleverer and wiser than I am
and what is it about his work and
obviously having spent time with him as
well that you find interesting the point
about Richard and you would never find
this I think in the UK is that he
teaches at a place called C I s the
California Institute of integral studies
in which he's deal
with almost everything that's really
important and looking at all the
influences on us that are normally
gnawed by modern science I meet these
people whenever I stop working in a bit
of time off because they're talking
about what I think really matters and a
lot of it would be regarded as very
strange my the volvo i mean if i sat at
it in a table in london and started
talking about the afterlife which i
believe through these people that
there's ample evidence that something
goes on the table would go quiet because
they would be embarrassed that I'd gone
off my rocker and I think that this is
an indication of just how crazy the
intellectual world I won't say has
become as it may always have been like
this but how crazy the intellectual
world is I mean for 60 years we learned
that fats for the course of heart
disease then suddenly we discover oh no
they're not its it sugar well 60 years
you know in behaviorism which is simply
observing what you can observe and then
pretending everything else doesn't exist
which is insane in itself you know that
dominated psychology for 60 years what
annoys me about says it's not they make
a lot of mistakes but they are so
resistant to changing their mistakes and
I think it's because nobody likes to
change paradigms if their previous work
was dependent on the paradigm because it
devalues their work if somebody
certainly says well the theory you based
it on isn't quite right so I mean
there's a lot of people talking about
the need for a paradigm shift and I
guess Richard on a sandy McGilchrist are
both involved in whatever that might
look like
you've obviously been interested in this
for a while what do you make of what
what is the paradigm shift that's needed
do you think well it's to move away from
the idea that this is a reductionist
materialist universe which a lot of
obviously very clever people
like Dawkins and Steven Pinker are
absolute dead settle and I think it's
from what I know and after all these are
my ideas I just hear other people's
ideas and I think I can spot good ones
this is a ridiculous and the evidence
that disproves it just gets pushed out
of the way I mean Rupert Sheldrake whom
I admire greatly was on television BBC
of course science department which is a
very primitive sort of production is
reductionist of the department I went on
was with Dawkins and when Dawkins became
very dismissive I mean I shall raign
asked him about the stuff that Sheldrake
had sent him to read and and Dawkins
said I didn't bother to read it because
it knows nonsense which is like Galileo
saying you know when he'd invented the
telescope and he invites the top fever
from the Catholic Church he says please
come and look through my beautiful new
telescope to see the craters on the moon
and the Scholastic's a gallon a we don't
need to look through a telescope we know
they're not there now we laugh at that
medieval church we have a lot of the
similar feelings in today's science and
in McGilchrist work talks about the left
brain and the right brain as different
ways of looking at the world the left
brain very atomistic reductionist and
the right brain much more open to nuance
and the mystery what why do you think
that's a really significant because I
don't think that the world is a very
happy place and IANS point really is
that the left brain likes to dominate or
left hemisphere likes to dominate the
right hemisphere and it seems to have
the weapons because it's very you know
it has speech on its side it's very
strong in speech the left brain wants to
control and exploit and produce and
analyze and divide in order to find out
more about it was the right brain sees
the whole thing and it's in the right
hemisphere that we get our feelings that
mean
for this in life which i think is why so
many of the philosophers are rather
depressed because there in the left
brain and of course that's the stuff
they write because if you're happy you
write happy things and have happy
thoughts and if you're sad you write sad
things because you have sad thought so
until we get the sort of reget regain
the balance that I think we had but Ian
thinks that goes back as far as the
Enlightenment which was a moment when
people sort of said get rid of that
right hemisphere way of relating to it
make everything very analytic in the
sort of Darwinian sense that that they
do that the universe could only be
understood as a piece of clockman and
decent as a connection to comedy they're
the right brain yes III I do I think
that people who are very very analytical
tend not to have very good senses of
comedy or if they do it would be a very
narrow kind of comedy the sort of wit
comedy whereas the part of us that loves
absurd situations like $40 if you if
you're too stuck in your left hemisphere
you won't think of that as funny you
know just think what an idiot and both
Richard and Ian are considered sort of
spiritual looking at the spiritual world
how would you describe your kind of
religious or spiritual orientation well
I think again that there's lots going on
that modern science denies but I think
the great sadness is that you will start
with a religious leader and you finish
that with an organized Church and any
kind of religion that I think is
worthwhile is to do with trying to break
down the power of our egos and if you
look at the Beatitudes which is the
heart of Christ's teaching when he says
blesses of the meekness into the
peacemakers peacemakers or cheesemakers
one of the thing it's
oh yeah when when when Jesus is at the
attitude he says blessed are the pure in
heart you know bless the poor in spirit
versus the meat but is a piece but this
is about people who are not running
around sticking their chest out and
saying how important they are it's about
a quietness do you see what I mean and a
receptiveness which means that maybe
some kind of divine and Stuart divine
experience can come through if you get
in that mood which is why some of the
more interesting origins emphasize
meditation you see what I mean but the
moment that people come along they and
they say not to Christ but to people
like Christ well well you could have
gotta get organized you you know we need
a marketing department and what you
finish up with is the Catholic Church
which is supposed to be teaching Christ
teaching which is humility poverty and
tolerance and of course it's a very rich
powerful authoritarian organization and
this is the ultimate paradox isn't the
lightest word and that's the problem
with organized religion whereas I think
there are people sometimes who have
insights into what religion is really
about where they don't think they're
very good at organizing except for the
Buddhists who insist on personal
transmission so it's not lost because
people read books and misunderstand them
because they're at a low level of
spiritual development and I understand
you've met the Dalai Lama yes how was
that was wonderful I was injured I was
asked if I wanted to meet him and I said
well of course and I went up and I
thought well I'll try not to say
everything too but now like you know
where did you get your sandal so how was
this particular reincarnation going so I
stood there waiting for the spirit to
move me and I just started laughing and
he started laughing and we stood there
laughing together for about 15 seconds
and then I said thank you very much and
the something about being around that
man and those think are made
was that you suddenly become Li as I
secret just ago you suddenly become less
worried about making a fool of yourself
of this worried about letting something
slip which will embarrass you and you've
become much more relaxed hmm and we've
had a lot of people on our channel talk
about what we're calling the the meaning
crisis the crisis of meaning or the
god-shaped hole in the culture even
though that's underneath a lot of a lot
of what with a lot of the conflict and
division that we're seeing yes I think
that was a time when people had some
sort of feeling that their lives were
meaningful and I think that
intellectuals that came along and you
know the existentialist and so forth it
was a meaningless universe do you know
you might as well just do anything
because you know at least it's authentic
for you and I don't think happiness
lives that way and I think if people
just sat and meditated for 10 minutes a
day I think the country would become
much happier in about 4 days people have
forgotten what's important and money has
become all-important particularly sadly
in England now in the way that it used
to be in America but it's now in England
with that kind of mindset I don't think
we can expect much to happen but you
never know I mean I remember I was with
two family therapists once and they said
very kindly about a couple they'd been
seeing I think they one of them said I
think that what this couple needs is a
nice crisis because people only change
in crises so maybe there will be a
crisis yeah but I think if people
actually started to think what might
make me happy in other other than not
what like maybe richer or more important
people would become much happier or
straightaway be familiar at all with
Jordan Peterson I know that Jordan
Peterson has fallen foul of the PC crowd
which means he must be good because Ian
McGilchrist had a really interesting
conversation with Jordan Peterson the
that was sort of this incredible
exploratory conversation about religious
truth and the structure of the mind and
the brain
but you have to remember now that
religion is just a bad thing and things
are either good or bad and we have this
kind of binary thing in feeling now
somebody's good or bad which is cause
nothing to do with real life as my
mother used to say we're super there she
would say as good and bad in all of us
and this idea that certain things are
good and certain things are bad you take
someone like colonial the idea of
Jainism
all right it's largely bad but there
were also good things and people would
get very angry with a true mom say no no
it was all bad at all times and then
that's associated with white skinned
people you say one of the Muslims have
done quite a lot of colonialism was that
in any way better than the white skinned
you see what I mean we're all much more
mixed up they don't stop trying to
pretend one thing is all good and one
thing is all bad because that's the
definition of paranoia and then you get
into denial and projection where the
things that you deny and your self your
projection to other people you see in
them and then there's absolutely no
chance of compromise which the English
historians used to say the English ever
had a genius for compromise not anymore
have you ever been on the receiving end
of any of this PC police
oh yeah eight years ago I said that
London wasn't an English city anymore
which is immediately taken as a
racialist remark I mean I'm all in favor
of people staying with their cultures if
they come to England you know they
should bring their Caribbean culture
with them or whatever of course they
were but they should also be interested
in the the culture of the country to
which they come it's old-fashioned thing
with its When in Rome do as the Romans I
mean if I was going to live in another
country the first thing I do is learn
the language and then I would find out a
bit about the history and maybe a little
bit about the literature but what I see
is the English culture just fading away
because nobody bothers to
promote it at all but everyone else's
culture is more important no they're all
important and I also don't think that
all cultures are equal for example a
culture that actually turns a blind eye
or even tolerates female genital
mutilation is not as good as a culture
that doesn't but that will make people
go who you just say that's my opinion
because there was some press coverage
accusing you of racism for that so
there's a difference between racism and
culturalism that is if you are of a
particular race there's not much you can
do about it but so far as culture's
concern you can choose exactly which
culture or which cultures you like so
you have freedom to choose with culture
and that's what I'm talking about I'm
not talking about color I mean most of
the time most of the trouble and London
at the moment is that the nice houses in
the centre of London have been brought
up by Ukrainian oligarchs we've paid 40
million spent another 20 million on it
and it's for their auntie or their
mother-in-law who then comes to London
for weeks in the year and leaves the
place empty for 48 weeks in the year
what one Belgravia it's absolutely
deserted well is that a good thing
I don't know how are you crazy too but
it's all of them dominating the culture
I don't really one side he preaches that
sort of racing up the down Sloane Street
the small hours of the morning I mean
that's not English and also we have a
lot of knife pride now what I would say
I don't remember that forty years ago it
was that people didn't use knives in
those days so there's a lot of changes
taking place and in some ways I prefer
the old England which I think was more
tolerant and more humorous and more
relaxed and took things a little bit
more easily you know the thing I
remember from history was Sir Francis
print a few no he's on
on the bowling-green in Plymouth and
they say sir francis the armed artists
on the way and francis says yeah well
they won't be here for some time let's
finish the game it was that sort of
quality which you don't really see much
of these days so I regret that going but
I don't want a cosmopolitan ization of
all cities if I go to Berlin I like it
to feel vaguely German if I go to Rome
I'd like it to feel vaguely Italian is
it the shrillness of the culture angry
about you know I mean young people are
angry because they can't get into the
property market in London and I'm
totally sympathetic with that and the
reason is that the extremely rich people
from completely undemocratic societies
and now to dominate the property market
in London and people young people can't
get their foot on the ladder that's
wrong hmm and what I find really
interesting about this kind of fury over
the last couple of weeks is that one of
the big things that drove bricks it was
people's feeling this isn't my country
anymore and I think you put your your
finger on that kind of division as well
yes I mean I spoke out because I knew it
would upset people and when you've as
old as I am when you've upset people as
regularly as I did right from pride you
know that the whole thing just passes
it's just storm in a teacup in churches
as a storming in espresso cup so was it
deliberate yes or no yeah I love getting
people cross with and I don't think
they're very smart because I can then
ask them questions like when I when they
I said that I thought that race was
genetic now it doesn't seem to me to be
an inflammatory comment I mean you
expect people of color to have children
of color and white people to have white
children I mean it seems to me there's
some sort of connection between genetics
and race and then a lot of geneticists
write to me and say no there's no such
thing as race and so I think well why
don't you better tell the race relations
people and they have obviously got to
come up with a new
I don't know people get excited and they
don't really listen to what I say but I
make a huge difference between culture
and race I believe races are completely
equal in the sense that they have all
the rights that any other race head I
mean I noticed that some people run
faster than others another swim better
than others and that's in itself
interesting so we're not perhaps equal
in every single way because some people
are more talented here and less talented
there and there's always a great thing
about race about intelligence well I'm
one of those people who's read Howard
gardener and I know that there's lots of
different type of intelligence and you
can be very high on what intelligence
and very low on another like have you
ever seen a philosopher dance we'll see
what I mean so I just feel that it
provided with Suri's be kind and
friendly to each other we can let go of
these beliefs which are really largely
wrong and which seems to divide people
much more than they right if we go back
to a life of Brian religious taboos were
still part of the culture they don't
seem to be so much a part of the culture
anymore and there's there's a new set of
taboos that's right the new set of
taboos is is quite different I mean
though now we can get away with really
very bad language by the standards of
the sixties and seventies but at the
same time we could make fun of the major
and he could be explaining to his
girlfriend what was the difference
between a whopping a Dago and we could
all laugh in it and now people take it
seriously no that was making fun of
prejudice not but people can't see that
it's like people who used to see elf
beyond it and say well fine I thank god
these things are finally being said I
mean there's that there's that there's a
group of people out there who just don't
get what words mean because they are
strangers to irony or they're just plain
ignorant well they just haven't thought
about things and it's not bad to stir
them up I think because summer but the
support you said there was a fear or the
support I've had has been extraordinary
I mean none of my friends disagrees with
me they'll say no it isn't an English
anymore and these aren't my friends
aren't racist where they're everyone
says of course it was a very funny thing
on YouTube at the moment I don't know if
you've seen this young comedian on
YouTube it's terribly funny my daughter
said it to me this morning but I think
the nice thing is we do just have a
sense of humor and what people don't
understand is that teasing which a lot
of national jokes you know jokes like
why do they French have so many civil
war so they can win one now and again
you know we can all laugh at a joke like
that people love that joke this mean we
hate the French so there's two types of
teasing there's nasty teasing and this
affectionate teasing and when were with
our friends a family forget together we
tease each other all the time it helps
us to bond it's part of showing
affection nasty teaching we don't want
don't throw out the baby with the
bathwater they're no longer around
religion where are they where the taboos
in society well I mean we're now in
terms of comedy I mean well yes in terms
of Tantra comedy you have to be very
careful about anything to do with what
it's now called gender which was of
course was a term appropriated from
grammar you have to be very careful so
you have to be very careful there
because people get offended but you see
what people do you think it's really a
moral act to get offended and I say no
I'm offended all the time every time I
read a news item I'm offended
particularly if Trump is involved you
know it all offends me
but that doesn't mean I'm going to go
out and try and stop people saying and
doing these things because if that's
what they want to do I handle my sense
of offense and the moment you start
trying to stop people being offended
then they can't control their emotion so
they have to try and control other
people's behavior and you get the most
neurotic the most touchy the most
hypersensitive people say this is the
moral standard that we now have
no no no you're the most touching people
you like you're like the maiden aunts or
made an uncle screw you see what I mean
don't try and impose that on us because
this is not what we want and what sort
of people these you know it reminds me
of the old definition of a Scottish
presbyterian or somebody has a nasty
feeling that somebody somewhere is
enjoying themselves you know
it's that sort of mind disapproving it's
phony a lot of it because a lot of its
posturing because they love this warm
glow of self-righteousness when they
protected not themselves of course but
somebody else you know and I think 90%
of it is species started off as
a good idea let's not be horrible and
cruel and kind of people and then it
became this blanket thing which it looks
as though it's trying to exterminate
humor and fun what what do you hope for
your legacy ah what I'm not interested
in leaving a legacy I want to spend
every penny I got there my children
regard themselves raising pastors John
Cleese thank you very much for your time
okay and that'll get rid of trouble
you
[Music]